<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>General Relativity and Quantum Cosmology on Chris Frohmaier</title>
    <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/tags/general-relativity-and-quantum-cosmology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in General Relativity and Quantum Cosmology on Chris Frohmaier</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/tags/general-relativity-and-quantum-cosmology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Illuminating gravitational waves: A concordant picture of photons from a neutron star merger</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1710.05436/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1710.05436/</guid>
      <description>Merging neutron stars offer an excellent laboratory for simultaneously studying strong-field gravity and matter in extreme environments. We establish the physical association of an electromagnetic counterpart (EM170817) with gravitational waves (GW170817) detected from merging neutron stars. By synthesizing a panchromatic data set, we demonstrate that merging neutron stars are a long-sought production site forging heavy elements by r-process nucleosynthesis. The weak gamma rays seen in EM170817 are dissimilar to classical short gamma-ray bursts with ultrarelativistic jets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-messenger Observations of a Binary Neutron Star Merger</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1710.05833/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1710.05833/</guid>
      <description>On 2017 August 17 a binary neutron star coalescence candidate (later designated GW170817) with merger time 12:41:04 UTC was observed through gravitational waves by the Advanced LIGO and Advanced Virgo detectors. The Fermi Gamma-ray Burst Monitor independently detected a gamma-ray burst (GRB 170817A) with a time delay of ensuremathsim 1.7 s with respect to the merger time. From the gravitational-wave signal, the source was initially localized to a sky region of 31 deg^2 at a luminosity distance of 40_-8^+8 Mpc and with component masses consistent with neutron stars.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
