<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Astrophysics - Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics on Chris Frohmaier</title>
    <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/tags/astrophysics-instrumentation-and-methods-for-astrophysics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Astrophysics - Instrumentation and Methods for Astrophysics on Chris Frohmaier</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/tags/astrophysics-instrumentation-and-methods-for-astrophysics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Real-time Recovery Efficiencies and Performance of the Palomar Transient Factory&#39;s Transient Discovery Pipeline</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1704.02951/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1704.02951/</guid>
      <description>We present the transient source detection efficiencies of the Palomar Transient Factory (PTF), parameterizing the number of transients that PTF found versus the number of similar transients that occurred over the same period in the survey search area but were missed. PTF was an optical sky survey carried out with the Palomar 48 inch telescope over 2009-2012, observing more than 8000 square degrees of sky with cadences of between one and five days, locating around 50,000 non-moving transient sources, and spectroscopically confirming around 1900 supernovae.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The dark energy survey 5-yr photometrically identified type Ia supernovae</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2201.11142/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2201.11142/</guid>
      <description>As part of the cosmology analysis using Type Ia Supernovae (SN Ia) in the Dark Energy Survey (DES), we present photometrically identified SN Ia samples using multiband light curves and host galaxy redshifts. For this analysis, we use the photometric classification framework SUPERNNOVAtrained on realistic DES-like simulations. For reliable classification, we process the DES SN programme (DES-SN) data and introduce improvements to the classifier architecture, obtaining classification accuracies of more than 98 per cent on simulations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PISCOLA: a data-driven transient light-curve fitter</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2110.11340/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2110.11340/</guid>
      <description>Forthcoming time-domain surveys, such as the Rubin Observatory Legacy Survey of Space and Time, will vastly increase samples of supernovae (SNe) and other optical transients, requiring new data-driven techniques to analyse their photometric light curves. Here, we present the &amp;lsquo;Python for Intelligent Supernova- COsmology Light-curve Analysis&amp;rsquo; (PISCOLA ), an open source data- driven light-curve fitter using Gaussian Processes that can estimate rest-frame light curves of transients without the need for an underlying light-curve template.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing a magnitude-limited spectroscopic training sample for photometric classification of supernovae</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2012.12122/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2012.12122/</guid>
      <description>In preparation for photometric classification of transients from the Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) we run tests with different training data sets. Using estimates of the depth to which the 4-m Multi-Object Spectroscopic Telescope (4MOST) Time Domain Extragalactic Survey (TiDES) can classify transients, we simulate a magnitude-limited sample reaching r_AB ensuremathapprox 22.5 mag. We run our simulations with the software SNMACHINE, a photometric classification pipeline using machine learning. The machine-learning algorithms struggle to classify supernovae when the training sample is magnitude limited, in contrast to representative training samples.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
