<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>methods: data analysis on Chris Frohmaier</title>
    <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/tags/methods-data-analysis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in methods: data analysis on Chris Frohmaier</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/tags/methods-data-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>From core collapse to superluminous: the rates of massive stellar explosions from the Palomar Transient Factory</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2010.15270/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2010.15270/</guid>
      <description>We present measurements of the local core-collapse supernova (CCSN) rate using SN discoveries from the Palomar Transient Factory (PTF). We use a Monte Carlo simulation of hundreds of millions of SN light-curve realizations coupled with the detailed PTF survey detection efficiencies to forward model the SN rates in PTF. Using a sample of 86 CCSNe, including 26 stripped-envelope SNe (SESNe), we show that the overall CCSN volumetric rate is r^mathrmCC_v=9.10_-1.27^+1.56times 10^-5, textSNe yr^-1, textMpc^-3, h_70^3 at = 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The volumetric rate of normal type Ia supernovae in the local Universe discovered by the Palomar Transient Factory</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1903.08580/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1903.08580/</guid>
      <description>We present the volumetric rate of normal type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia) discovered by the Palomar Transient Factory (PTF). Using strict data-quality cuts, and considering only periods when the PTF maintained a regular cadence, PTF discovered 90 SNe Ia at z ensuremathleq 0.09 in a well-controlled sample over three years of operation (2010-2012). We use this to calculate the volumetric rate of SN Ia events by comparing this sample to simulations of hundreds of millions of SN Ia light curves produced in statistically representative realizations of the PTF survey.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-time Recovery Efficiencies and Performance of the Palomar Transient Factory&#39;s Transient Discovery Pipeline</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1704.02951/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1704.02951/</guid>
      <description>We present the transient source detection efficiencies of the Palomar Transient Factory (PTF), parameterizing the number of transients that PTF found versus the number of similar transients that occurred over the same period in the survey search area but were missed. PTF was an optical sky survey carried out with the Palomar 48 inch telescope over 2009-2012, observing more than 8000 square degrees of sky with cadences of between one and five days, locating around 50,000 non-moving transient sources, and spectroscopically confirming around 1900 supernovae.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The dark energy survey 5-yr photometrically identified type Ia supernovae</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2201.11142/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2201.11142/</guid>
      <description>As part of the cosmology analysis using Type Ia Supernovae (SN Ia) in the Dark Energy Survey (DES), we present photometrically identified SN Ia samples using multiband light curves and host galaxy redshifts. For this analysis, we use the photometric classification framework SUPERNNOVAtrained on realistic DES-like simulations. For reliable classification, we process the DES SN programme (DES-SN) data and introduce improvements to the classifier architecture, obtaining classification accuracies of more than 98 per cent on simulations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing a magnitude-limited spectroscopic training sample for photometric classification of supernovae</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2012.12122/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2012.12122/</guid>
      <description>In preparation for photometric classification of transients from the Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) we run tests with different training data sets. Using estimates of the depth to which the 4-m Multi-Object Spectroscopic Telescope (4MOST) Time Domain Extragalactic Survey (TiDES) can classify transients, we simulate a magnitude-limited sample reaching r_AB ensuremathapprox 22.5 mag. We run our simulations with the software SNMACHINE, a photometric classification pipeline using machine learning. The machine-learning algorithms struggle to classify supernovae when the training sample is magnitude limited, in contrast to representative training samples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spectrophotometric templates for core-collapse supernovae and their application in simulations of time-domain surveys</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1908.05228/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1908.05228/</guid>
      <description>The design and analysis of time-domain sky surveys require the ability to simulate accurately realistic populations of core-collapse supernova (SN) events. We present a set of spectral time-series templates designed for this purpose, for both hydrogen-rich (Type II, IIn, and IIb) and stripped-envelope (Type Ib, Ic, and Ic-BL) core-collapse SNe. We use photometric and spectroscopic data for 67 core-collapse SNe from the literature, and for each generate a time-series spectral template.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
