<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Astrophysics - Solar and Stellar Astrophysics on Chris Frohmaier</title>
    <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/tags/astrophysics-solar-and-stellar-astrophysics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Astrophysics - Solar and Stellar Astrophysics on Chris Frohmaier</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/tags/astrophysics-solar-and-stellar-astrophysics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Panning for gold, but finding helium: Discovery of the ultra-stripped supernova SN 2019wxt from gravitational-wave follow-up observations</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2208.09000/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2208.09000/</guid>
      <description>We present the results from multi-wavelength observations of a transient discovered during an intensive follow-up campaign of S191213g, a gravitational wave (GW) event reported by the LIGO-Virgo Collaboration as a possible binary neutron star merger in a low latency search. This search yielded SN 2019wxt, a young transient in a galaxy whose sky position (in the 80per cent GW contour) and distance (ensuremathsim150 Mpc) were plausibly compatible with the localisation uncertainty of the GW event.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PISCOLA: a data-driven transient light-curve fitter</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2110.11340/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2110.11340/</guid>
      <description>Forthcoming time-domain surveys, such as the Rubin Observatory Legacy Survey of Space and Time, will vastly increase samples of supernovae (SNe) and other optical transients, requiring new data-driven techniques to analyse their photometric light curves. Here, we present the &amp;lsquo;Python for Intelligent Supernova- COsmology Light-curve Analysis&amp;rsquo; (PISCOLA ), an open source data- driven light-curve fitter using Gaussian Processes that can estimate rest-frame light curves of transients without the need for an underlying light-curve template.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Observing the earliest moments of supernovae using strong gravitational lenses</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2003.14340/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_2003.14340/</guid>
      <description>We determine the viability of exploiting lensing time delays to observe strongly gravitationally lensed supernovae (gLSNe) from first light. Assuming a plausible discovery strategy, the Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) and the Zwicky Transient Facility (ZTF) will discover ensuremathsim110 and ensuremathsim1 systems per year before the supernova (SN) explosion in the final image, respectively. Systems will be identified 11.7^+29.8_-9.3 d before the final explosion. We then explore the possibility of performing early-time observations for Type IIP and Type Ia SNe in LSST-discovered systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using late-time optical and near-infrared spectra to constrain Type Ia supernova explosion properties</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1803.10252/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1803.10252/</guid>
      <description>The late-time spectra of Type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia) are powerful probes of the underlying physics of their explosions. We investigate the late-time optical and near-infrared spectra of seven SNe Ia obtained at the VLT with XShooter at &amp;gt;200 d after explosion. At these epochs, the inner Fe-rich ejecta can be studied. We use a line-fitting analysis to determine the relative line fluxes, velocity shifts, and line widths of prominent features contributing to the spectra ([Fe II], [Ni II], and [Co III]).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Illuminating gravitational waves: A concordant picture of photons from a neutron star merger</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1710.05436/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1710.05436/</guid>
      <description>Merging neutron stars offer an excellent laboratory for simultaneously studying strong-field gravity and matter in extreme environments. We establish the physical association of an electromagnetic counterpart (EM170817) with gravitational waves (GW170817) detected from merging neutron stars. By synthesizing a panchromatic data set, we demonstrate that merging neutron stars are a long-sought production site forging heavy elements by r-process nucleosynthesis. The weak gamma rays seen in EM170817 are dissimilar to classical short gamma-ray bursts with ultrarelativistic jets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early observations of the nearby Type Ia supernova SN 2015F</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1609.04465/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1609.04465/</guid>
      <description>We present photometry and time series spectroscopy of the nearby Type Ia supernova (SN Ia) SN 2015F over -16 d to +80 d relative to maximum light, obtained as part of the Public ESO Spectroscopic Survey of Transient Objects. SN 2015F is a slightly sub-luminous SN Ia with a decline rate of ensuremathDeltam_15(B) = 1.35 ensuremathpm 0.03 mag, placing it in the region between normal and SN 1991bg-like events. Our densely sampled photometric data place tight constraints on the epoch of first light and form of the early-time light curve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Search for an Optical Counterpart to the Gravitational-wave Event GW151226</title>
      <link>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1606.04795/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://chrisfrohmaier.github.io/publications/paper_1606.04795/</guid>
      <description>We present a search for an electromagnetic counterpart of the gravitational-wave source GW151226. Using the Pan-STARRS1 telescope we mapped out 290 square degrees in the optical I _P1 filter, starting 11.5 hr after the LIGO information release and lasting for an additional 28 days. The first observations started 49.5 hr after the time of the GW151226 detection. We typically reached sensitivity limits of I _P1 = 20.3-20.8 and covered 26.5per cent of the LIGO probability skymap.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
